Myrthe Reuver

Computational Linguist, Data Scientist, PhD Candidate

Researcher and PhD Candidate (started: Sept 2020) at the Free University of Amsterdam (VU), advisors: prof. dr. Antske Fokkens (VU) and dr. Suzan Verberne (Leiden University). My research is on NLP to support democracy in news recommendation, and my broader interest is in **societally and scientifically responsible NLP in complex domains**, and in computationally unpacking complex concepts

CV last edited: July 4, 2022

♦ https://myrthereuver.github.io/▶ myrthe.reuver[at]vu.nl↑ myrthereuver↑ Twitter: @myrthereuver

Research Experience

PhD candidate: NLP for Diversity in News Recommendation

2020 - present

Free University of Amsterdam (VU)

- Work on language technology to automatically detect (viewpoint) diversity in news texts, to design a democracy-supporting news recommender.
- o Supervisors: prof. dr. Antske Fokkens (VU) and dr. Suzan Verberne (Leiden University)

Internship: Graduation Projects Clinical Natural Language Processing

2019 - 2020

Topicus Healthcare, Deventer

- o MSc thesis on classification of complaint category in emergency GP triage (huisartsenpost)
- o ResMA thesis on smoking status detection in EMRs with weak supervision & transfer learning

Research MA Internship: Classifying Urban Legends

2019

Meertens Institute, Amsterdam

Results: popular science article in Neerlandistiek, a conference presentation

at DHBenelux 2019, poster presentation at CLIN (CompLing in the Netherlands) in 2020.

Participant "ICT with Industry" research week

2019

Lorentz Centre, Leiden

- Developing a prototype of an automatic keyword classifier for the National Library (Koninklijke Bibliotheek, KB).
- o Results: a demo prototype, a report, and an NWO Science vlog.

MA Honours Project: Thinking Machines in Healthcare

2017 - 2018

Radboud Honours Academy & REShape Innovation, Nijmegen

o 1-year Honours think tank with master students from different disciplines on prototyping an AI for people with type 2 Diabetes.

BA Honours Project: Text Mining in Old English

2014 - 2016

Radboud Honours Academy, Nijmegen

o 2-year research project, included Text Mining summer school in Aarhus, Denmark.

Student Research Assistent

2014 - 2017

English Department, Radboud University

- o Student assistant in research projects, mostly in historical English and Dutch.
- Tasks: data annotation and data cleaning/ preprocessing.

Education

2018 - 2020Master of Science (MSc) Cognitive Science & Artificial Intelligence Tilburg University o GPA: 7.9 / 10 (with distinction) o Thesis: "What Kind of Emergency? Complaint Labels for Dutch Short Clinical Texts" (Grade: 8/10) o Courses (selection): Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Advanced Data Processing with Python Research MA Linguistics, track: Language & Speech Technology 2017 - 2020Radboud University o GPA: 8.3 / 10 (cum laude) o Thesis: "Finding the Smoke Signal: Smoking Status Extraction & Classification" (Grade: 8 / 10) o Internship: Classifying Urban Legends at the Meertens Institute (Grade: 9 / 10) o Courses (selection): Text & Multimedia Mining, Language & Speech Technology, Advanced Statistics in R BA English Language & Culture, specialization: Linguistics 2014 - 2017Radboud University • GPA: 8.6 / 10 (cum laude) o certificate BA Honours Program: 2-year Text Mining Project + Summerschool Aarhus University, Denmark. Bachelor of Journalism, first-year diploma 2012 - 2013Christelijke Hogeschool Ede (CHE) Radio Presenter at "Radio Almelo" (AAFM) 2007 - 2012HAVO (higher general secondary education) OPDC 't Nijrees Almelo Summer & Winter Schools.... o "Research Integrity" Summer Seminar, Netherlands Research Integrity Network. 2021 o "Trolls, bots and dictators" Summer School. Digital Methods Initiative, Uni of Amsterdam 2019 o "Text Mining for the Humanities" Summer School Aarhus University, Denmark. 2016 **Awards and Grants** Small interdisciplinary grant "Reasons for online (dis)trust in sustainable initiatives" 2022 IWDS Call, VU Network Institute - with dr. Ana Lopez (Communication Science) Winning team Hackathon "Designing a Diverse-aware Recommender System" 2020 NPO (Dutch Public Broadcaster) and Media Perspectives Teaching & Supervision Teacher BA + MA course "Programming in Python for Text" 2021 Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam Teaching Assistant BA course "Information Science" 2018 - 2020Radboud University Nijmegen Supervision..... ReMA thesis - Operationalizing Fragmentation for News Recommendation - 2022, co-supervised with prof.dr.Antske Fokkens & Sanne Vrijenhoek (UvA)

Academic Leadership & Service

Founder & Editor-in-Chief student journal RU:ts

2018 - 2020

Academic Service.

o On-Site Student Volunteer: EMNLP 2021, RecSys2021, CLIN28 (2018)

Reviewing Experience.

- o **Journals:** Computational Communication Science Journal (2021-), Transactions on Information Systems (2022-)
- o Conferences: SIGIR 2021 (subreviewer), SIGIR (2022 -)

Skills

- o Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing
- o (Academic) Writing
- Public Speaking and Presenting
- o Cloud Computing, Linux, bash scripting

Languages

- Python including huggingface, sklearn & pandas, R proficient
- o html & css, familiar
- o Dutch, mothertongue, (Academic) English, C2 (near-Native)
- o German, B2 (decent), Latin, B1 (basic)

Publications

Papers

- Myrthe Reuver, Suzan Verberne, Morante Roser, and Antske Fokkens. Is stance detection topic-independent
 and cross-topic generalizable? A reproduction study. In: Proceedings of the 8th Workshop on Argument
 Mining, co-located at EMNLP 2021, pages 46–56, Punta Cana, Dominican Republic, 2021. Association for
 Computational Linguistics. <u>URL</u>.
- o Myrthe Reuver, Nicolas Mattis, Marijn Sax, Suzan Verberne, Nava Tintarev, Natali Helberger, Judith Moeller, Sanne Vrijenhoek, Antske Fokkens, and Wouter van Atteveldt. Are we human, or are we users? The role ofnatural language processing in human-centric news recommenders that nudge users to diverse content. In: *Proceedings of the 1st Workshop on NLP for Positive Impact*, co-located at ACL-IJCNLP 2021, pages 47–59. Association for Computational Linguistics, 2021. URL.
- Myrthe Reuver, Antske Fokkens, and Suzan Verberne. No NLP task should be an island: Multi-disciplinarity for diversity in news recommender systems. In: Proceedings of the EACL Hackashop on News Media Content Analysis and Automated Report Generation, pages 45–55. Association for Computational Linguistics, 2021. URL.

Peer Reviewed Abstracts and Posters

- o Myrthe Reuver, Nicolas Mattis, Marijn Sax, Suzan Verberne, Nava Tintarev, Natali Helberger, Judith Moeller, Sanne Vrijenhoek, Antske Fokkens, and Wouter van Atteveldt. "Are we human, or are we users? The role of natural language processing in human-centric news recommenders that nudge users to diverse content." Poster at Interdisciplinarity on the Digital Society, Network Institute. URL.
- o Myrthe Reuver, Suzan Verberne, Roser Morante and Antske Fokkens. 9 July 2021. "Viewpoints in the news: claim detection for diverse news recommendation." Poster at Computational Linguistics in the Netherlands (CLIN) 31 (Online), 9 July 2021. URL.
- o Myrthe Reuver, Iris Hendrickx, Jeroen Kuijpers. "Smoking Status Detection with a Pre-Trained Transformer and Weak Supervision in Dutch Electronic Patient Files." Talk at Computational Linguistics in the Netherlandsa (CLIN) 31 (Online), 9 July 2021. URL.

- o Myrthe Reuver. "How Similar are Poodles in the Microwave? Classification of Urban Legend Types". Poster at Computational Linguistics in the Netherlands (CLIN) 30, Utrecht, January 2020. URL.
- o Myrthe Reuver. "Making the Computer Understand Urban Legend Types (And Making Humans Understand the Computer)". Moving Humanities Graduate Conference, Nijmegen: 24 October 2019. URL.
- Myrthe Reuver. "Amputation or Accident? Classifying Dutch Urban Legends into Story Types with a Hierarchical Classifier". Digital Humanities BeNeLuX, Liège: 13 Sept 2019. URL.
- o Myrthe Reuver. "Whose Gender is It? Possessive Pronoun Errors by Portuguese L2 speakers of English." 13th TWIST Student Conference in Linguistics, Leiden. 13 April 2019. URL.
- o Myrthe Reuver. "First-Person Visibility: Ælfric's Pronouns in his Prefaces.", StuTs Student Linguistics Conference, Nijmegen. 24 November 2017. URL.

Popular Science

- o Myrthe Reuver. (2021) "5 Things I Learned During the First Year of my PhD." Blog post. <u>URL</u>
- Myrthe Reuver, Nicolas Mattis. (2020) "Hackers of Science: Lessons from interdisciplinary science in a Hackathon" Socializing Science, blog post. <u>URL</u>
- o Myrthe Reuver. (2019). "Hoe een computer broodjeaapverhalen leert categoriseren." Vertelcultuur Online. URL
- o Myrthe Reuver. Vlog for research week "ICT with Industry". URL

Reports (Not Peer Reviewed)

- Myrthe Reuver, Nicolas Mattis. (2021). "Implementing Evaluation Metrics Based on Theories of Democracy in News Comment Recommendation (Hackathon Report)" In: Proceedings of the EACL Hackashop on News Media Content Analysis and Automated Report Generation (co-located at EACL 2021, online). Association of Computational Linguistics, p. 134–139. URL
- o Anthony Burton, Elena Aversa, Alessandra Facchin, Ivana Emily Škoro, Henri Mütschele, **Myrthe Reuver**, Shenglang Qing. (2019). "Streams of the Deep Web: Rebel Media, YouTube, and the algorithmic shaping of media ecosystems." Digital Methods Wiki, UvA Summerschool. URL
- o Brandsen, A., Kleppe, M., Veldhoen, S., Zijdeman, R., Huurman, H., Vos, H. De, Goes, K., Huang, L., Kim, A., Mesbah, S., **Reuver, M.**, Wang, S., Hendrickx, I. (2019). "Brinkeys.." KB Lab:The Hague, the Netherlands. URL

Book Reviews

 Myrthe Reuver (2022) Summary & Book Review of "Linguistics for the Age of AI". In: The Linguist List 33.135. URL

Talks

Invited Talks

- o Myrthe Reuver. "Viewpoint diversity in news recommendation: Theories, Models, and Tasks to support democracy". MilaNLP Lab, Bocconi University (Milan). Online. 1 July 2022. Slides
- Myrthe Reuver. "Hackathons, Shared Tasks, and Papers: Collaboration and Interdisciplinarity with Data on Complex Problems". Free University of Amsterdam, University Library Data Conversations. Online. 7 April 2021. Video

Media Appearances

- May 2022. Uitsmijter: De Macht van Algoritmen. Interview in Dutch computer magazine "Computer Idee" about my fight with a credit scoring algorithm and also my research, and the use of algorithmic solutions in society. URL
- 18 January 2022. Zo werd Myrthe Reuver de dupe van haar data: 'Ze geloven in eerste instantie het systeem'.
 Interview and article in national newspaper Trouw about my experiences with the credit scoring algorithm of the Dutch National Railways (NS). URL